<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>For every individuall member of the honourable House of Commons. Concerning the major, magstracy, and officers of Dover.</title>
            <author>Burt, Nathaniel, fl. 1644-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E568_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206270</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865442</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865442</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78012)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 87:E568[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>For every individuall member of the honourable House of Commons. Concerning the major, magstracy, and officers of Dover.</title>
                  <author>Burt, Nathaniel, fl. 1644-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated on p. [8]: London, August 8. 1649. Nathaniell Burt Junior.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 9th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:165316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>For every individuall Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons. <hi>Concerning the Major, Magſtracy, and Officers of Dover.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <note place="margin">
               <p>ACcording to what is mentioned in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, one of my ſervices to my Native Countrey, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and City of my birth; was the ſerveing an Order from Grocers Hall, when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment retired thither for ſafety upon the breach of Parliament priviledges, and the demand of five of their Members: and I beleeve M. <hi>Corbets</hi> hand to it, which Order I ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon Sir <hi>John Byron</hi> L. of the Tower, when none would readily attempt it, but my ſelfe, as ſome Citizens which yet are living can teſtifie; and then amongſt the rest I watched the Tower, both by Land, and Water, as Order was given, leaſt Iriſh men ſhould be let in for a guarde, and it ſhould be victualled alſo, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the diſmounting the Cannons then moun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in <hi>Terrorem,</hi> both to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and City.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> The gaining Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> of wapping a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and diſcyplineing himſelfe and others for Officers, and about <hi>140.</hi> volonteeres, ſouldiers for any preſent Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſervice, in which I was L. to Cap. <hi>Willoughby,</hi> and was with him, and theſe my fellow ſouldiers at the ſecuring of Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, and Eſſex Block-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, when Kent oppoſed (many of them) the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as Col. <hi>Dean</hi> can teſtifie, who I believed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs now to the Navy as an Admirall, and was then imployed in Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end Fort, for and by my Cap. <hi>Willoughby;</hi> but whither or no Col. <hi>Deane</hi> remembers I had no pay in this ſervice, can I not tell, as in my other I am ſure I had none at all.</p>
               <p>Then I was with Cap. <hi>Willoughby</hi> to ſecure the Royall Soveraigne, a ſhip ſo called, lay at <hi>Gilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> which it was feared the Kentiſh men ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifie, at another time, and <hi>I</hi> ſet a Guard and Watch upon it, till afterward the Guns, Tackle and Officers were removed, and yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing paid to me.</p>
               <p>Sirs, you may plainly ſee how <hi>Willoughby</hi> may well be rich, and I poor, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived money.</p>
               <p>Amongſt my many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices I went to Chicheſter in Suſſex, I ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now in part of Col. <hi>Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies</hi> knowledge, and ſpent neere <hi>4.</hi> moneths time before I returned, whiles the Forces were raiſing, proceeding to Arundel, and had taken in Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, wherein I was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Captains pay for my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance therin, as ſome yet ſurely remember: And I was paid with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for after we had by Gods bleſſing poſſeſed our ſelves as of Arundel, ſo of Chicheſter, my place I had ſerved in under L. Col. <hi>Roberts,</hi> Col. <hi>Stapely</hi> not being preſent by reaſon he was ſick, was by him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſold or given away for ſome reward to a Lawyer of <hi>Lewis,</hi> who had not at all ingaged, or ſome one advanced to make way for him: and I was colourably confined to my Chamber, and ſet before a Councell of Warre, where my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary was my Judge, when <hi>Sir William Waller</hi> was departed, and he wanting matter of charge to lay on me, made me prove how I came by money to maintain my ſelf while I was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in that ſervice, which being proved by Cap. <hi>Temple</hi> of Eſſex Block Houſe, a Suſſex Gent. ſince a Col. who at firſt perſwaded me to go into that Countrey, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I had received money of my Col. Sir <hi>William Brookes</hi> at Graves End, who had disbanded by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not only for my pay, as his Cap. L. But alſo for the Trophies of Armes for his Regiment, for which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged my ſelf to one Maſter <hi>Webſter</hi> in Milk ſtreet London, an Armourer, or ſuch like, which moneys I carried along with me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and out of which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys I paid Cap. <hi>Temple</hi> at his own houſe in Suſſex, where he lodged me the first night, for a Bay nagg he ſold me, which was loſt in the ſaid ſervice, for which entertainment I thank Cap. <hi>Temple,</hi> but I do not thank him for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sir <hi>Richard Laſhfords</hi> ſword, I tooke when I commanded a party to the Lady <hi>Shellies</hi> at Michell Grove, by Col. <hi>Morleyes</hi> Order, and others, to ſearch her houſe, where I took Sir <hi>Richard Laſhford;</hi> and ſome Letters then come from Oxford, which was a great furtherance to our taking in of Chicheſter; and upon Cap. <hi>Temples</hi> knowledge of this truth, and others testimony, I was quitted at the Councell of Warr, and L. Col. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> gave me his paſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand and ſeal, which I believe I can yet produce, which was as though I had leave given me to viſite my family for ſome time, and then to return to the ſaid ſervice again; and I did not onely here ſpend a ſumme of money of my own, and M. <hi>Webſters,</hi> which is ſince ſatisfied, but was alſo coſened and defrauded of my promiſed pay, and yet never received any pay at all for Suſſex ſervice, one thing I had like to have forgotten, I was ſent out from Lewis in Suſſex, with a party and a Commiſſion, or warrant to feize upon the man ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, which ſince was made Lord Culpepper, but remanded back, by a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which was written, muſt be burnt by me at my return, which Letter, and Warrant, or Commiſſion, I believe I have ſtill, and becauſe I then diſliked it I was after that abuſed; as before related, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in part, both before and after this, I had, and and was faithfull and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant to diſcover Armes brought by water, and to ſeize them when I had warrants, as will appear under many of the Lords and Commons hands; and all gratis, without either bribe, pay or part datained, or converted to, or for my own uſe; (which is enough to ſpend a vaſt eſtate, which I am ſure my deare wife and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and other my friends have found by woefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.) After this I yet helped my Cap. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby</hi> again, hoping he would be honeſter, the times requiring it, England growing into a lower con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, and hee amongſt divers others had vowed to Almighty God, ſo to be by Covenant: This made me accept of a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains place under his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; he to be the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Officer, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſaid Regiment which indeed I ſhould have been the Major of the ſaid Regiment, for I was the firſt Cap. and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to diſperſe the ſeverall Commiſſions, and to raiſe and forme the ſaid Regiment: And though I lost my right of Majorſhip, I did not then deſert the ſaid ſervice, as I beleeve M. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> one of the Committee at Salters Hal, doth or may remember, which is ſince Lord Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, who then laboured with me to deny my ſelfe, and refer my place and ſelf to the ſaid Committee, which I then did: but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment goes by favour, more then true and reall deſervings, but how the ſaid <hi>Willoughby</hi> abuſed me and defrauded me againe, I have ſufficiently ſet forth in my proteſt made againſt him, printed and poſted upon the Royall Exchange, and other places, Anno <hi>1644.</hi> For which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I was impriſoned in Mayden lane Priſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat <hi>4.</hi> moneths; becauſe forſooth I had expreſſed therein that the then <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> Committee of London, after ſo long debate and report made thereupon, kept my report from me, and would not do me Juſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tice, which is truth: after theſe my loſſes and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, and trialls by two ſeverall Councells of Warre, and ſeverall ſuits by this cauſed, and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination of ſome was coſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of my leaſe of the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Wapping in my low eſtate, being beaten out of trading which coſt me a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout <hi>230</hi> l. beſides other houſhold goods: And I went L. to ſea, with one Cap. <hi>Hodges</hi> in the Lorne Frigot, no purchaſe, no pay, and after <hi>5.</hi> moneths ſervice being poſſeſſed with purchaſe, yet never had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhares, though they did amount to neere <hi>150.</hi> l. upon this I ſet up to work at Dover: and you that read this my Epiſtle, It was not for riches and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, or favour of men onely, that I engaged in this cauſe, but for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and favour of God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrist, which ſaith, <hi>8.</hi> Mark <hi>35.36. But whoſoever ſhall loſe his life for my ſake, and the Goſpell, he ſhall find it. For what ſhall it profit a man, though he ſhould win the whole world if he loſe his ſoule?</hi> Thus I have truly related ſome part of my ſervices, and ſufferings: yet never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any advance money, place, profit, aſſiſtance in trouble, juſtice upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, or reward when others have been provided for by place, or rewarded that have not done or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. <hi>100.</hi> fold, what I have done, but my reward is with <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
               </p>
            </note>
            <p>BEing incouraged by former preſidents to you ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally preſented, and by your favourable receiving thereof and proſecution therein for divers of my Brethren, fellow-ſouldiers, and Citizens; It hath likewiſe imboldened me who am a free-borne Engliſh-man, and free Denizon, who am thereby intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto equall priviledge with any of my rank, or diſcent, by which the Freedome and Liberties of the Lawes of England are intailed to me and mine, borne in England, or to be hereafter borne: beſides, the right that I have by right of Conqueſt, and as 23. October, 1642. 1 part of your Book of Declar. pag. 660. and our Truſtees in Parliament then declared, they were ready to lay downe their lives to preſerve, affirming our Laws and Liberties the greateſt earthly treaſure we could or can here poſſeſſe, and likewiſe adjudged thoſe who would not help in the day of their ſtraights prophane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> who would ſell their birth-rights, and vaſſallage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir poſterity. Now before this time God ſtirred me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p to ſtand and act for Englands freedome, and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Priviledge, who had inabled me to withſtand the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llegality of Ship-money, and other abuſes offered my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare Countrey-men, and fellow-Citizens, as alſo in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower of London to withſtand hainous things of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tructive nature to the Subjects Priviledge, where I lived <hi>Anno</hi> 1638. and were by ſome there practiſed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe I would not conſent thereunto, I loſt my Tower-place, and profits, as I have in other places done ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all times ſince, and am like now to loſe my Leaſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. years to come, and benefit of my Trade by thoſe mens oppreſſion and violence in Dover; alſo God made me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctive and couragious both at home and abroad, in thoſe Martiall abilities I was bleſt withall of, or from him, as
<pb facs="tcp:165316:2"/> Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> and many others may yet pleaſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
            <p>I am confident ſome hundreds yet can teſtifie what time the Houſe removed to Grocers-hall, in which ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (for my native Countreyes Liberty, and Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens ſafety, and Priviledges of Parliament) I have ſpent and loſt a faire eſtate, which London the place of my birth and kindred, is ſenſible of; yet God hath been pleaſed to keep me faithfull, and to uphold my ſpirit through all tyrannicall defrauding, oppreſſions and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall impriſonments I have ſeen, felt, and been under, both in London and many other places, indeed rather the ſubject of a book then a letter, and I never was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded or gratified with any place to reſtore my loſſes, neither have I purſued the ſame, but have laboured ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for bread for my wife and daughter, whom in the worlds eyes are undone by my zeale for my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes good, rather then to live on the Nations loſſe, which good I have alwaies promoted before my owne intereſt, or earthly profits, as Jehovah knoweth, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving read your Declaration alſo <hi>Die Sabbati,</hi> 17. <hi>Martii</hi> 1648. wherein you expreſſe the grounds of your late proceedings, and ſetling the preſent Government in the way of a free State, wherein you declare pag. 5. you are authorized for the common good, having contended againſt Tyranny, and to procure the well-being of thoſe people for whom you ſerve, to remove oppreſſion, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power, and all oppoſition to the peace and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Nation, and to prevent their power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive Tyrany, Injuſtice, War, and all our former evills; this hath very much incouraged me to proteſt againſt Mr. <hi>Day,</hi> as Mayor, and other Juſtices, and Common-Councell-men of Dover, and others, Conſtables, and grand Jury-men thereof, about 24, in number, who yet continue in places unſequeſtred, though they have been as active as any of thoſe which have been ſequeſtred for thoſe open rebellions, and Inſurrections in Wales, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey, and Kent, as is ſet forth in your Act for Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, with the reaſon and grounds thereof, <hi>die Veneris,</hi> 1 <hi>Junii,</hi> 1649. that you and the Army had not been
<pb facs="tcp:165316:2"/> thereby deſtroyed by the revolt of divers Caſtles at once, and the defection of a great part of the Navy; theſe men many of them continue at this time in place, who are mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and proteſted againſt by me for their hypocriſie and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, theſe are termes in the ſaid Act by you expreſſed, pag. 275. 276. theſe promoted that perfidious Ingagement by ſuch an Authority, which might denominate the breach Nationall, who yet corruptly ſide and combine together, ruling according to their wills, and not Law, they upholding a Monopoly in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, called the Leather-Corporation, which was never granted by Parliament, for which they in my ſight at one time received ſix pound of money in Dover-Court, taking their goods away by force, or otherwayes, which will not obey thereunto, and impriſoning and proſecuting all thoſe to deſtroy them by ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and delaying Suits in Law, who oppoſe their arbitrary wills, yet they exact it expreſſely againſt Law, which things you declare to be againſt that excellent Law of the Petition of Right done in the Perſon of the late King, who was tried for the ſame, and why ſhould not theſe alſo be tried, as Declar. 17. <hi>Martii,</hi> pag. 7. &amp; 14. and theſe Anti-Magiſtraticall, Anti-Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries, hold only the place, ruling by power and policy, not by reaſon and honeſty, they being tyrannicall creatures, though to the world pretend otherwiſe, according as their linſey-wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey Prieſt <hi>John Dix</hi> hath in his Negative Oath plainly diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all judicious and impartiall judgements, yet theſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Parliament are againſt their choice or ſitting, if cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, or their Voice to chuſe, they being uncapable by ſome of theſe Ordinances of Parliament, <hi>die Junii,</hi> 9. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1647. 4, <hi>Octobris,</hi> 1647. by which theſe men outed their neighbours of Dover both from Voice and Choice, as they outed <hi>Edward Ranger</hi> June the 8. 1648. by Act of Common-Councell from the Foot-Poſts place of Dover, for that he bare Armes in the Ingagement 1648. for which he hath been ſequeſtred and hath agreed it, yet many of them have done the ſame which are here charged, a faire preſident for themſelves. Againe, Londons Preſident, a rule ſure for the whole Land where Corporations are to chooſe Officers, <hi>die Lunae,</hi> 18. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1648. for the chooſing of Common-Councell-men for the yeer inſuing, and other Officers within the City of London, and the Liberties thereof; and <hi>die Mercurii,</hi> 20. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1648. the Lords and
<pb facs="tcp:165316:3"/> Commons doe ordain, that no perſon whatſoever that ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, promoted, or abetted any Ingagement in the years 1648. or the treaſonable Ingagement 1647. or relating to a perſonall Treaty with the King at London, ſhall be choſen Mayor, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman, or put into any of the offices or places expreſſed upon the penalty of two hundred pound, by which Ordinances Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is made obedient, though theſe Dover-men preſume to ſit Mayor, Jurats, or Juſtices, Common-Councell-men, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and other Officers, contrary to all theſe Parliament-Ordinances, and other preſidents of London, Yarmouth, and Weymouth, they being ſequeſtrable as well as other their neighbours before ſpecified, in that they have been aiding ſome of them, by ſubſcribing the Petitions, others promoting and abetting the Ingagement, 1648. for which your humble Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant being a free Commoner of England, beſides his proteſt he made againſt them in the Seſſions at Dover, <hi>May</hi> 24. 1649. in the name of all free-borne Engliſh-men, which have not forfeited it, and in the name of the Supreme Authority of this Nation, and ſince hath petitioned alſo the honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Indempnity againſt them and their proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Parliament-Ordinances, and London, and other Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; yet ſtill theſe continue their places of truſt, and upon your Petitioners Proteſt <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> theſe men on the 29. of <hi>May,</hi> 1649. with the aſſiſtance of ſome other, ordered your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to be committed to Dover-Caſtle without Baile or Maine-prize, perſwading Capt. <hi>Dixall</hi> (a Member of this Houſe, then at Dover, he being the Burgeſſe thereof) that I was a Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere; but I ſuſpecting their malicious and illegall practiſes, came away from Dover about foure houres before the Caſtle-Souldiers came to my houſe to take me into their cuſtody, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſtrongly urged by others ſo to do. Now I appeal to you, whether I am a Mutineere for labouring to do the Nation and you faithfull ſervice and right: What, becauſe I claime the Law of the Land? which as Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in his Expoſition of 29. <hi>Cap.</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> diſtinction 3. <hi>Law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is called right, becauſe it is the best right the Subject hath, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his goods, lands, wife, children, his body, life, honour, and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation are protected from injuries and wrong, it being</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>the ſureſt ſanctuary that a man can take, and the ſtrongest fortreſſe to protect the weakeſt of all, to every one of us there comes a greater
<pb facs="tcp:165316:3"/> inheritance by right and the law, then by our Parents;</hi> and for pleading this Law for my right and protection, and for ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for my legall-Liberties given me by the Law of the Land, and your Declarations, Ordinances and Acts; theſe men of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which ſit as Magiſtrates, yet act Anti-Magiſtraticall, they make their wills a Law againſt me, become Judges in their own cauſes, making me fly from my houſe, family and trade, for protection from their exorbitant wills, they living in a Sea-Port Towne, where no <hi>habeas Corpus</hi> they will ſuffer to be granted, though themſelves would have the benefit of the Law, ſo that no Law can or ſhal take place againſt their luſts &amp; corrupt wils, for they hinder any copie of Indictment, or any elſ to be taken out to adviſe on, and the Lawyers there as well as the Prieſts are joyned in the work of their corrupt intereſt the better to vaſſallage the minds of the ignorant, or fearfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to uphold their own dignity and wealth, which muſt be of all the people Idolized through cringing, and readily believing, honouring and obeying to them in their corrupt intereſts to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves and deſtroy the people; as the <hi>leane and evill favoured kine did devoure the ſeven fat kine, and it could not be knowne they were ſo evill favoured, Gen.</hi> 41.20, 21. though they had eaten them up, ſo theſe juggle and diſſemble with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſay, they have not done them wrong, but many of us are ſenſible theſe of Dover, as well as others, do ſuch things and do wrong, which further to illuſtrate that they might keep the Inhabitants thereof in fear, <hi>July</hi> 13. being Friday, they ſent for me to come to them to their Court at Dover, by one <hi>Walter Smith</hi> that then attended them, which I refuſed, telling the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> that they ought firſt to appeare to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt them in the honorable Committee of Indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity at Weſtminſter, I having ſummoned them ſo to do above fourteen daies ſince, and I then going away to attend my try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all there, which meſſage <hi>Smith</hi> having returned, they preſently ſend one <hi>John Filly,</hi> who ſaid he was a Conſtable, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he had a Warrant from Court to bring me before them, who was accompanied with about ſix perſons more, and two of them, if not three, Conſtables, who had borne Armes in the Ingagement 1648. in that Rebellion and Inſurrection, Dover-Caſtle being kept by the Parliament Forces, and ſtraightned and beſieged by the County and Towneſmen of
<pb facs="tcp:165316:4"/> Dover, of which force ſome of theſe men are part now char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Committee in the Inner Court of Wards, to which they have appeared unto, though eleven of the twelve charged never yet was ſequeſtred. Now I was forced to complaine here becauſe of the great hypocriſie, partiality, and injuſtice I ſaw uſed by theſe men and their friends, in the ſaid Towne and County, and moſt of the Town of Dover being actors in the ſaid open Rebellion, howſoever they would conceale it or hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically cover it, moſt of them being of kin, or cemented by ſome ſelfe-intereſt, or profit, and trade, and ſo loath to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover one another, leaſt they ſhould loſe the friendſhip of this world, which is enmity with God and goodneſſe; thus men live by ſenſe more then by faith: Now the reaſon <hi>Filly</hi> with his guard of incapable Conſtables took me not by force, was becauſe my door being ſhut, which was as a hatch very low, though <hi>Filly</hi> told the aſſiſtants to him, if they would aſſiſt him therein he would break open my door, and fetch me out with a witneſſe, I then ſtood in my defence, and ſo I told them, and would not yeeld my ſelfe, but withall I pulled out the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Order of the Committe under M. <hi>Miles Corbets</hi> hand, then Chair-man, dated <hi>June</hi> 11. 1649. which <hi>Filly</hi> had heard on ſufficiently, yet <hi>Filly</hi> would not reſpect or obey it, ſaying, what if this be M. <hi>Corbets</hi> hand, I know him well enough, but what is M. <hi>Corbets</hi> hand worth in this place? ſaying, he would make me obey his Warrant, but would not let me ſee it neere enough to read it; at length <hi>Filly</hi> departed, and bid the other ſtay of his aſſiſtants, ſaying, he would go and fetch, or receive other Orders, upon which it was rumoured by the Towne people, that theſe <hi>roaring Lyons or ravening Wolves, would break my bones e're evening,</hi> as <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.3, for ſaid they, ſhift for your ſelf, or els they of the Town-Hall will procure a Squadron of Souldies from Dover-Caſtle to take you, that they might have their wills of you, thus they would uſe any means to ſatisfie their envy, they invite the abuſive ſouldiery againſt me, or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the people they would, upon which I cauſed my ſhop to be quite ſhut up, and retired my ſelfe private for my more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity and peace, knowing too well how my reſpective friend M. <hi>Henry Teddyman</hi> was abuſed by the rude Souldiery then in Dover-Caſtle, who came downe ſome number about Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember laſt to him, to have him up to the Caſtle upon ſome
<pb facs="tcp:165316:4"/> conceited affront, for which they would be their owne Judges, whereof ſee the effect, M. <hi>Teddyman</hi> would not render him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but told them he would be anſwerable by Law, theſe giddy, bloody, unreaſonable ſouldiers ſhoot in at his ſhut doors, and ſhot his wife big with child, and killed his daughter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bout thirteen yeers of age by ſhot, and then went up to the Caſtle againe without the man; a lamentable ſtory to tell, but very true, though few of Dover would lay it to heart, but ſhuffled it off I now not how, though the Mayor, which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurps the place, M. <hi>Day</hi> knew it too well; for he was Mrs. <hi>Teddy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Chyrurgion till ſhe was recovered, and for this blood no body ſufferen, either by Law Common, or Martiall, which miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe of warre to prevent, and malice of my adverſaries, I was forced to fly to London againe the ſecond time, and for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afety of my deere wife and daughter, which is all the children I have left of ten, ſince I have been contending in the field for freedome, right, and liberty, as invited by your Declar. 23. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tober, before ſpecified, yet muſt I now fly or die, it may be my wife and daughter too as M. <hi>Teddymans</hi> child before ſpoken of, or lie in priſon to ſatisfie the corrupt wills and ravenous affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of my covetous, tyrannicall, oppreſſing Judges at Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who amongſt them have ſought my ruine ever ſince I came among them, becauſe I would not joyne with them to work unrighteouſneſſe, to rob and oppreſſe free-born Engliſh-men, who have not forfeited their freedomes, ſome of them being of a forraigne blood or line, and favour a forraigner more then an Engliſh-man, but that almoſt al ſhould do ſo, makes me much admire, and yet no man calleth for Juſtice, no man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth for truth, as the Prophet complaines, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.4. and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>rather reprove the works of darkneſſe, then have fellowſhip with them, Eph.</hi> 5.11. but it is no new thing to be hated therefore, for it was ſo of old, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10. <hi>they have ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed him that rebuked in the gates, and they have abhorred him that ſpeaketh uprightly;</hi> and this forraigne kindred or Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, meddles not with men, but for their corrupt intereſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know they Engliſh-mens priviledges, yea [too few En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-men now do yet know it] why, ſaith our Saviour, when he was on the earth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>He that doth evill hateth the light least his deeds ſhould be reproved; but he that doth truth cometh to the light to manifeſt that they are wrought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:165316:5"/>
            <p>I would ask mine oppreſſors and the peoples, why by force or fraud, injuſtice or connivance, they ſeek to deſtroy me, as by their power of Judicature and Councell though uſurped, and yet (ſay they beleeve) I will anſwer them, and all who ſit in power and place and do ſo. Firſt from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. v. 23. <hi>Hath the throne of iniquity fellowſhip with thee.</hi> Secondly, wirh one of your own Declar. 1. part Book Decla. pag. 150. Magiſtrates are appointed for the protection and preſervation, but not ruine or deſtruction of the people, and the Mayor yet threatneth to lay me faſt enough at Dover; and by the Lawes of this Land, no man is to be Judge in his own caſe. 8. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>fol.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 5. <hi>Eliz. Dicr.</hi> 220. and Doctor <hi>Bonhams</hi> caſe, eight part of <hi>Cooks</hi> reports. But could theſe Dover men, of uſurped place and power have gotten me to their Guild-Hall, or by their power and policy, have gotten me into their Goale; or Dover Caſtle, They would then, and their having all power in their hands, as a ſeaport Town: and the Burgeſſe, and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers their friends, have been complaynants, perſecutors, witeneſſes, Jury and Judges of me as of <hi>Edward Ranger,</hi> and <hi>Hedge</hi> his man, and of <hi>Edward Chambers</hi> lately they have been: then you may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, what would have become of me amongſt them, when ſome of them were ſo audacious, unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and unmannerly, as to give me ſcurrilous and ſore threatning language, on Wedneſday and Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 26. and 27. of July laſt paſt in and about the Court of Wardes, as M. <hi>Day,</hi> M. <hi>Dell,</hi> M. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Knot,</hi> and M. <hi>Henry Hart,</hi> as <hi>John Filly</hi> and <hi>John Kenton</hi> had done, <hi>July</hi> the 24. when <hi>Filly</hi> ſware a negative oath, or told an untruth, at which time ſome Officers of Court, <hi>viz.</hi> M. <hi>Kerke,</hi> M. <hi>Leichman,</hi> and M. <hi>Danet</hi> reproved them, and cauſed <hi>Filly</hi> and <hi>Kenton</hi> to go out of their room for their uncivill affronts in language: Now the caſe depending in the inner Court of Wardes, and much proved againſt moſt of them, all but one, though nine witneſſes are not yet appeared, 12. by me is charged, as by the Articles and the Examinations taken, will appear upon hearing, wherefore, I humbly intreat you to take it into your ſerious conſideration, againſt Friday the 10. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> inſtant, which is appointed by conſent (if the witneſſes fail not) that ſo the caſe may be looked on without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either the Plantifs or Defendants, power or meaneſs: <hi>Ye ſhall do no unrighteouſneſſe in Judgement. Thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the Mighty, but in righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy neighbour. Levit.</hi> 19.15. Ye ſhall not reſpect perſons in Judgement; but you ſhall heare the ſmall, as well as the great; you ſhall not be afraid of the face of man, for the Judgement is Gods.</p>
            <p>Thus I commit my cauſe and my ſelfe, to your examination and tryall; which by your own Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Declarations named, appears to be the Nations and Peoples, who hath entruſted you, and you, and the People of the Nation into the hand of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the faithfull Creator, bleſſed for Evermore, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours next the Almighties, to procure truth and Right. <hi>Nathaniell Burt Junior.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>Auguſt 8. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
